[{"question":"1.The process of forecasting or approximating the time and cost of completing project deliverables is called\nA.Budgeting\nB.Predicting\nC.Estimating\nD.Planning\nE.Guesstimating","type":"multipleChoice","answer":"C.","help":"Estimating is the process of forecasting or approximating the time and cost of completing project deliverables.","difficulty":"Level: Easy"},{"question":"2.In practice, estimating processes are frequently classified as\nA.Top down/bottom up\nB.Rough/polished\nC.Precise/order of magnitude\nD.Draft/final\nE.Both A and B are correct","type":"multipleChoice","answer":"A.","help":"Estimating processes are frequently classified as top-down and bottom-up. Top-down estimates are usually doneby senior management.","difficulty":"Level: Easy"},{"question":"3.A typical statement in actual practice is that estimates should have a probability of being met ______ of thetime.\nA.100%\nB.98%\nC.95%\nD.90%\nE.80%","type":"multipleChoice","answer":"C.","help":"But past experience estimates must almost always be refined by other considerations to reach the 95 percent probability","difficulty":"Level: Easy"},{"question":"4.A good starting point for developing time and cost estimates is\nA.Past experience\nB.Work packages\nC.Task analysis\nD.Time and motion studies\nE.Work breakdown structure","type":"multipleChoice","answer":"A.","help":"Past experience is a good starting point for developing time and cost estimates.","difficulty":"Level: Easy"},{"question":"5.Which of the following is not one of the factors that need to be considered to improve quality of estimates for project times and costs?\nA.Planning horizon\nB.People\nC.Padding estimates\nD.Profit\nE.Project structure","type":"multipleChoice","answer":"D.","help":"See List on Page 128-129.","difficulty":"Level: Medium"},{"question":"6.Ed is looking over the actual results of projects and comparing them to what was estimated. He notices that projectsthat took six months or longer to complete were noticeably more off the estimates. Which of the followingfactors is he recognizing?\nA.Padding estimates\nB.Planning horizon\nC.Project structure\nD.People\nE.Organization culture","type":"multipleChoice","answer":"B.","help":"The quality of the estimate depends on the planning horizon; estimates of current events are close to 100 percentaccurate but are reduced for more distant events. The accuracy of time and cost estimates should improveas you move from the conceptual phase to the point where individual work packages are defined.","difficulty":"Level: Medium"},{"question":"7.Janet is forecasting how much money her department needs to support a new project. She estimates that two peopleand $25,000 in expenses will cover her needs. Because management typically insists on reducing forecastsby 20 percent, she increases her estimates to allow for that reduction. Which of the following factors isillustrated in this situation?\nA.Padding estimates\nB.Planning horizon\nC.Project structure\nD.People\nE.Organization culture","type":"multipleChoice","answer":"A.","help":"In work situations where you are asked for time and cost estimates, most of us are inclined to add a little paddingto increase the probability and reduce the risk of being late. If everyone at all levels of the project addsa little padding to reduce risk, the project duration and cost are seriously overstated.","difficulty":"Level: Medium"},{"question":"8.Which of the following is a good condition for top-down estimating?\nA.Cost and time important\nB.Fixed price contract\nC.Customer wants details\nD.Internal, small project\nE.All of these are good conditions for top-down estimating","type":"multipleChoice","answer":"D.","help":"See table 5-1 on Page 132.","difficulty":"Level: Medium"},{"question":"9.Which of the following is a good condition for bottom-up estimating?\nA.Strategic decision making\nB.Internal, small project\nC.Fixed price contract\nD.High uncertainty\nE.Both C and D are good conditions for bottom-up estimating","type":"multipleChoice","answer":"C.","help":"See table 5-1 on Page 132.","difficulty":"Level: Medium"},{"question":"10.Top-down estimates are most likely to occur during the ______ phase.\nA.Concept\nB.Planning\nC.Execution\nD.Delivery\nE.All of these are equally likely","type":"multipleChoice","answer":"A.","help":"Top-down estimates are only a rough cut and typically occur in the \"conceptual\" stage of the project.","difficulty":"Level: Easy"},{"question":"11.______ estimates are most likely to use low cost, efficient methods.\nA.Apportion\nB.Ratio\nC.Top-down\nD.Bottom-up\nE.All of these are equally likely","type":"multipleChoice","answer":"D.","help":"The bottom-up approach also provides the customer with an opportunity to compare the low-cost, efficient methodapproach with any imposed restrictions.","difficulty":"Level: Medium"},{"question":"12.Which of the following methods is not considered a top-down approach to estimating project time and cost?\nA.Ratio\nB.Template\nC.Apportion\nD.Function point\nE.Learning curve","type":"multipleChoice","answer":"B.","help":"Template Methods are used in bottom-down approach to estimating.","difficulty":"Level: Medium"},{"question":"13.Jose is forecasting project time and cost for constructing a new building by multiplying the total square footageby a given dollar amount. Which of the following methods is he using?\nA.Ratio\nB.Template\nC.Apportion\nD.Function point\nE.Learning curve","type":"multipleChoice","answer":"A.","help":"Top-down methods (sometimes called parametric) usually use ratios, or surrogates, to estimate project times orcosts. Top-down approaches are often used in the concept or \"need\" phase of a project to get an initial durationand cost estimate for the project.","difficulty":"Level: Medium"},{"question":"14.Sean is forecasting the time and cost of developing a customized software program by looking at the number ofinputs, outputs, inquires, files, and interfaces. Which of the following methods is he using?\nA.Ratio\nB.Template\nC.Apportion\nD.Function point\nE.Learning curve","type":"multipleChoice","answer":"D.","help":"In the software industry, software development projects are frequently estimated using weighted macro variablescalled \"function points\" or major parameters such as number of inputs, number of outputs, number of inquiries,number of data files, and number of interfaces.","difficulty":"Level: Medium"},{"question":"15.Laura is forecasting the time and cost of developing an intranet for a new customer. Her department has completedsix such intranets for customers during the last two years. Although the proposed system is about the samesize as the others she estimates that it will take about 10 percent less time and money. Which of the followingmethods is she using?\nA.Ratio\nB.Template\nC.Apportion\nD.Function point\nE.Learning curve","type":"multipleChoice","answer":"E.","help":"A phenomenon of tasks that are labor intensive. In these circumstances the pattern of improvement phenomenoncan be used to predict the reduction in time to perform the task. From empirical evidence across all industries,the pattern of this improvement has been quantified in the learning curve (also known as improvement curve,experience curve, and industrial progress curve).","difficulty":"Level: Medium"},{"question":"16.Learning curves are more likely to apply in situations where most of the costs are\nA.Materials\nB.Labor\nC.Overhead\nD.Evenly spread over materials, labor, and overhead\nE.All of these are equally likely situations for learning curves","type":"multipleChoice","answer":"B.","help":"A phenomenon of tasks that are labor intensive. In these circumstances the pattern of improvement phenomenoncan be used to predict the reduction in time to perform the task. From empirical evidence across all industries,the pattern of this improvement has been quantified in the learning curve (also known as improvement curve,experience curve, and industrial progress curve).","difficulty":"Level: Medium"},{"question":"17.Which of the following is not one of the bottom-up approaches to estimating project time and cost?\nA.Parametric procedures applied to specific tasks\nB.Estimates for the WBS work packages\nC.Learning curve\nD.Template method\nE.All of these are bottom-up approaches","type":"multipleChoice","answer":"C.","help":"Learning curve is part of top-down approach to estimating.","difficulty":"Level: Medium"},{"question":"18.The approach that begins with a top-down estimate for the project and then refines estimates as the project isimplemented is known as ______ method.\nA.Function point\nB.Template\nC.Learning curve\nD.Phase estimating\nE.Apportion","type":"multipleChoice","answer":"D.","help":"This approach begins with a top-down estimate for the project and then refines estimates for phases of the projectas it is implemented.","difficulty":"Level: Easy"},{"question":"19.Which of the following would be the best method for projects where the final product is not known and the uncertaintyis very large?\nA.Function point\nB.Template\nC.Learning curve\nD.Phase estimating\nE.Apportion","type":"multipleChoice","answer":"D.","help":"Phase estimating is used when an unusual amount of uncertainty surrounds a project and it is impractical to estimatetimes and costs for the entire project.","difficulty":"Level: Medium"},{"question":"20.The accuracy of top-down estimates will typically be in the range of\nA.Minus 50% to plus 50%\nB.Minus 0% to plus 75%\nC.Minus 20% to plus 60%\nD.Minus 35% to plus 35%\nE.Minus 10% to plus 30%","type":"multipleChoice","answer":"C.","help":"See Table 5.4 on page 141.","difficulty":"Level: Medium"},{"question":"21.The accuracy of bottom-up estimates will typically be in the range of\nA.Minus 50% to plus 50%\nB.Minus 0% to plus 75%\nC.Minus 20% to plus 60%\nD.Minus 35% to plus 35%\nE.Minus 10% to plus 30%","type":"multipleChoice","answer":"E.","help":"See Table 5.4 on page 141.","difficulty":"Level: Medium"},{"question":"22.The cost to prepare bottom-up estimates will typically run how much more than the costs to prepare the top-downestimates?\nA.About the same\nB.About twice as much\nC.About three times as much\nD.About four times as much\nE.About five times as much","type":"multipleChoice","answer":"C.","help":"See Table 5.4 on page 141.","difficulty":"Level: Medium"},{"question":"23.Typical kinds of costs found in a project include\nA.Direct costs\nB.Project overhead costs\nC.General and administrative costs\nD.Only A and B are included\nE.A, B, and C are all included","type":"multipleChoice","answer":"E.","help":"See list on Page 142.","difficulty":"Level: Easy"},{"question":"24.Project costs are typically viewed from all of the following except:\nA.Scheduled\nB.Sunk\nC.Actual\nD.Committed\nE.All of these are correct","type":"multipleChoice","answer":"B.","help":"See Figure 5.6 on Page 143.","difficulty":"Level: Easy"},{"question":"25.Which of the following would be considered a direct project cost?\nA.Labor\nB.Materials\nC.Equipment\nD.Both A and B are direct costs\nE.A, B, and C are all considered direct costs","type":"multipleChoice","answer":"E.","help":"Direct project overhead costs can be tied to project deliverables or work packages. Examples include the salaryof the project manager and temporary rental space for the project team.","difficulty":"Level: Easy"},{"question":"26.Which of the following is not one of the recommended guidelines for developing useful work package estimates?\nA.Estimates should be made by those responsible for the work\nB.Use several people to estimate the same work\nC.Estimates should be based on normal conditions\nD.Estimates should include a normal level of contingency\nE.Estimates should be independent of other projects","type":"multipleChoice","answer":"D.","help":"See list on pages 144-145.","difficulty":"Level: Medium"},{"question":"27.Companies like Boeing, Kodak, and IBM are using which of the following for improving the estimating process?\nA.Adjusting estimates based on individual forecasting abilities\nB.Benchmarking using the experience of other companies\nC.Using time and motion studies\nD.Creating historical databases of previous projects\nE.All of these are correct","type":"multipleChoice","answer":"D.","help":"Some organizations have large estimating departments of professional estimators—e.g., Boeing, Kodak, IBM—thathave developed large time and cost databases.","difficulty":"Level: Easy"},{"question":"28.Reasons why estimating time and cost are important include all of the following except:\nA.To schedule work\nB.To determine how long the project should take and cost\nC.To develop cash flow needs\nD.To determine how well the project is progressing\nE.All of the above are valid reasons","type":"multipleChoice","answer":"E.","help":"See Exhibit 5.1 on Page 127.","difficulty":"Level: Easy"},{"question":"29.In a learning curve, the improvement ratio is applied to which of the following items?\nA.Direct materials\nB.Direct labor\nC.Overhead\nD.Both A and B are correct\nE.A, B, and C are all correct","type":"multipleChoice","answer":"B.","help":"These costs are clearly chargeable to a specific work package. Direct costs can be influenced by the projectmanager, project team, and individuals implementing the work package. These costs represent real cash outflowsand must be paid as the project progresses; therefore, direct costs are usually separated from overhead costs.Lower-level project rollups frequently include only direct costs.","difficulty":"Level: Medium"},{"question":"30.The bottom-up approach for estimating times and costs that uses costs from past projects that were similar tothe current project is known as:\nA.Detailed WBS work package estimates\nB.Template method\nC.Function point method\nD.Time-phased cost estimates\nE.Phase estimating","type":"multipleChoice","answer":"B.","help":"If the project is similar to past projects, the costs from past projects can be used as a starting point forthe new project. Differences in the new project can be noted and past times and costs adjusted to reflectthese differences.","difficulty":"Level: Easy"},{"question":"31.Which of the follow top-down methods is used when projects closely follow past projects in features and costsand result in costs being assigned by percentages to major segments of the project?\nA.Apportion\nB.Function point\nC.Phase estimating\nD.Learning curve\nE.Consensus","type":"multipleChoice","answer":"A.","help":"Apportionment is used when projects closely follow past projects in features and costs. Given good historicaldata, estimates can be made quickly with little effort and reasonable accuracy. This method is very commonin projects that are relatively standard but have some small variation or customization.","difficulty":"Level: Medium"},{"question":"32.Resource shortages, in the form of people, equipment, or materials, is a good example of\nA.Hidden interaction costs\nB.Things going wrong on a project\nC.Normal conditions not applying\nD.Changes in project scope\nE.None of these are correct","type":"multipleChoice","answer":"C.","help":"Estimates are supposed to be based on normal conditions. While this is a good starting point, it rarely holdstrue in real life. This is especially true when it comes to the availability of resources. Resource shortages,whether in the form of people, equipment, or materials, can extend original estimates.","difficulty":"Level: Medium"},{"question":"33.People working on prototype development needing time to interact with the design engineers after the design iscompleted is an example of:\nA.Hidden interaction costs\nB.Things going wrong on a project\nC.Normal conditions not applying\nD.Changes in project scope\nE.None of these are correct","type":"multipleChoice","answer":"A.","help":"Interaction costs are hidden in estimates. According to the guidelines, each task estimate is supposed to bedone independently. However, tasks are rarely completed in a vacuum. Work on one task is dependent upon priortasks, and the hand-offs between tasks require time and attention. For example, people working on prototypedevelopment need to interact with design engineers after the design is completed, whether to simply ask clarifyingquestions or to make adjustments in the original design.","difficulty":"Level: Medium"},{"question":"34.A manager getting further into a project and obtaining a better understanding of what needs to be done to accomplisha project is an example of:\nA.Hidden interaction costs\nB.Things going wrong on a project\nC.Normal conditions not applying\nD.Changes in project scope\nE.None of these are correct","type":"multipleChoice","answer":"D.","help":"As one gets further and further into the project, a manager obtains a better understanding of what needs to bedone to accomplish the project. This may lead to major changes in project plans and costs. Likewise, if theproject is a commercial project, changes often have to be made midstream to respond to new demands by thecustomer and/or competition.","difficulty":"Level: Medium"},{"question":"35.Design flaws being revealed after the fact, extreme weather conditions, and accidents occurring are examplesof:\nA.Hidden interaction costs\nB.Things going wrong on a project\nC.Normal conditions not applying\nD.Changes in project scope\nE.None of these are correct","type":"multipleChoice","answer":"B.","help":"Design flaws are revealed after the fact, extreme weather conditions occur, accidents happen, and so forth. Althoughyou shouldn't plan for these risks to happen when estimating a particular task, the likelihood and impactof such events need to be considered.Fill in the Blank Questions","difficulty":"Fill in the Blank Questions"},{"question":"36.Estimates that are typically based on estimates of elements found in the work breakdown structure are called________ estimates.","type":"fill-in","answer":"bottom-up","help":"The bottom-up approach at the work package level can serve as a check on cost elements in the WBS by rollingup the work packages and associated cost accounts to major deliverables.","difficulty":"Level: Easy"},{"question":"37.Estimates that are usually derived from analogy or mathematical relationships are called ________ estimates.","type":"fill-in","answer":"top-down","help":"Top-down estimates are usually done by senior management. Management will often derive estimates from analogy,group consensus, or mathematical relationships.","difficulty":"Level: Easy"},{"question":"38.The estimating factor known as ________ considers the decreasing accuracy of estimates as one forecasts activitiesthat are further into the future.","type":"fill-in","answer":"planning horizon","help":"The quality of the estimate depends on the planning horizon; estimates of current events are close to 100 percentaccurate but are reduced for more distant events. The accuracy of time and cost estimates should improveas you move from the conceptual phase to the point where individual work packages are defined.","difficulty":"Level: Medium"},{"question":"39.The ________ factor in estimating project times and costs can introduce errors due to staff turnover, the skillsof the participants, and whether the team members have worked with each other on previous projects.","type":"fill-in","answer":"people","help":"The people factor can also introduce errors in estimating times and cost. For example, accuracy of estimatesdepends on the skills of the people making the estimates. A close match of people skills to the task willinfluence productivity and learning time.","difficulty":"Level: Medium"},{"question":"40.The tendency to over-estimate project time and cost in order to improve the likelihood of meeting the estimatesis known as the ________ factor.","type":"fill-in","answer":"padding estimates","help":"In work situations where you are asked for time and cost estimates, most of us are inclined to add a little paddingto increase the probability and reduce the risk of being late. If everyone at all levels of the project addsa little padding to reduce risk, the project duration and cost are seriously overstated.","difficulty":"Level: Medium"},{"question":"41.The prevailing belief in some firms that detailed estimating takes too much time and is not worth the effortor that it is impossible to predict the future is an example of the ________ factor.","type":"fill-in","answer":"organization culture","help":"Organizations vary in the importance they attach to estimates. The prevailing belief in some organizations isthat detailed estimating takes too much time and is not worth the effort or that it's impossible to predictthe future. Other organizations subscribe to the belief that accurate estimates are the bedrock of effectiveproject management. Organization culture shapes every dimension of project management; estimating is notimmune to this influence.","difficulty":"Level: Medium"},{"question":"42.Using the _______ method of forecasting project time and costs is the preferred method for situations involvingstrategic decision-making, projects with a high degree of uncertainty, and projects with an unstable scope.","type":"fill-in","answer":"top-down","help":"See table 5-1 on Page 132.","difficulty":"Level: Medium"},{"question":"43.Using the ________ method of forecasting project time and costs is the preferred method for situations wherethe cost and time estimates are important, in a fixed contract situation, and when the customer wants a lotof detail.","type":"fill-in","answer":"bottom-up","help":"See table 5-1 on Page 132.","difficulty":"Level: Medium"},{"question":"44.The information necessary to conduct a bottom-up estimate of project time and costs starts with the ________.","type":"fill-in","answer":"work package","help":"If possible and practical, you want to push the estimating process down to the work package level for bottom-upestimates that establish low-cost, efficient methods. This process can take place after the project has beendefined in detail. Good sense suggests project estimates should come from the people most knowledgeable aboutthe estimate needed.","difficulty":"Level: Difficult"},{"question":"45.In the ________ method of top-down estimating, a quantitative relationship is established between the estimatesand a project parameter.","type":"fill-in","answer":"ratio","help":"Top-down methods (sometimes called parametric) usually use ratios, or surrogates, to estimate project times orcosts. Top-down approaches are often used in the concept or \"need\" phase of a project to get an initial durationand cost estimate for the project.","difficulty":"Level: Medium"},{"question":"46.Given that a project closely follows past projects in features and costs, the ________ method of assigns costsand times to particular phases that a project will go through.","type":"fill-in","answer":"apportion","help":"This method is an extension to the ratio method. Apportionment is used when projects closely follow past projectsin features and costs. Given good historical data, estimates can be made quickly with little effort and reasonableaccuracy. This method is very common in projects that are relatively standard but have some small variationor customization.","difficulty":"Level: Medium"},{"question":"47.The ________ method for estimating project time and cost uses weighted variables based on major parameters andis frequently used in the development of software.","type":"fill-in","answer":"function point","help":"In the software industry, software development projects are frequently estimated using weighted macro variablescalled \"function points\" or major parameters such as number of inputs, number of outputs, number of inquiries,number of data files, and number of interfaces.","difficulty":"Level: Medium"},{"question":"48.The ________ method of estimating project time and costs is useful for projects requiring the same task, groupof tasks, or product repeated several times, especially if it is labor intensive.","type":"fill-in","answer":"learning curve","help":"A phenomenon of tasks that are labor intensive. In these circumstances the pattern of improvement phenomenoncan be used to predict the reduction in time to perform the task. From empirical evidence across all industries,the pattern of this improvement has been quantified in the learning curve (also known as improvement curve,experience curve, and industrial progress curve).","difficulty":"Level: Medium"},{"question":"49.In the ________ method of estimating project time and costs past projects are used as a starting point with adjustmentsmade based on differences in the new project.","type":"fill-in","answer":"template","help":"If the project is similar to past projects, the costs from past projects can be used as a starting point forthe new project. Differences in the new project can be noted and past times and costs adjusted to reflectthese differences.","difficulty":"Level: Medium"},{"question":"50.Probably the most reliable method for estimating time and cost is to use the _______ and to ask the people responsiblefor the work package to make the estimates.","type":"fill-in","answer":"bottom-up","help":"If possible and practical, you want to push the estimating process down to the work package level for bottom-upestimates that establish low-cost, efficient methods. This process can take place after the project has beendefined in detail. Good sense suggests project estimates should come from the people most knowledgeable aboutthe estimate needed.","difficulty":"Level: Medium"},{"question":"51.The ________ approach to estimating project time and cost begins with an overall estimate for the project andthen refines estimates for various stages of the project as it is implemented.","type":"fill-in","answer":"phase estimating","help":"This approach begins with a top-down estimate for the project and then refines estimates for phases of the projectas it is implemented. Some projects by their nature cannot be rigorously defined because of the uncertaintyof design or the final product. Phase estimating is used when an unusual amount of uncertainty surroundsa project and it is impractical to estimate times and costs for the entire project.","difficulty":"Level: Medium"},{"question":"52.The cost to prepare a top-down budget will typically run ________ percent of the total project cost.","type":"fill-in","answer":"one-tenth to three tenths","help":"See Table 5.4 on page 141.","difficulty":"Level: Easy"},{"question":"53.The cost to prepare a bottom-up budget will typically run ________ percent of the total project cost.","type":"fill-in","answer":"three tenths to one","help":"See Table 5.4 on page 141.","difficulty":"Level: Easy"},{"question":"54.Project costs such as labor and materials are typically classified as ________ costs.","type":"fill-in","answer":"direct","help":"See list on Page 142.","difficulty":"Level: Easy"},{"question":"55.The salary of the project manager and temporary rental space for the project team would be classified as ________costs.","type":"fill-in","answer":"direct overhead","help":"Direct overhead rates more closely pinpoint which resources of the organization are being used in the project.Direct project overhead costs can be tied to project deliverables or work packages. Examples include thesalary of the project manager and temporary rental space for the project team.","difficulty":"Level: Medium"},{"question":"56.Estimates should be made based on ________ conditions, efficient methods, and a normal level of resources.","type":"fill-in","answer":"normal","help":"Estimates should be based on normal conditions, efficient methods, and a normal level of resources.","difficulty":"Level: Easy"},{"question":"57.The __________ method is a top-down approach that uses the pooled experience of senior and/or middle managersto estimate the total project duration and cost.","type":"fill-in","answer":"consensus","help":"The consensus simply uses the pooled experience of senior and/or middle managers to estimate the total projectduration and cost.","difficulty":"Level: Easy"},{"question":"58.Costs that are not directly related to a specific project, such as advertising, accounting, and senior management,are classified as ____________.","type":"fill-in","answer":"General and administrative overhead costs","help":"These represent organization costs that are not directly linked to a specific project. These costs are carriedfor the duration of the project.True / False Questions","difficulty":"True / False Questions"},{"question":"59.Project estimates should be broken down into as much detail than and with as much accuracy as possible.","type":"boolean","answer":"FALSE","help":"Detailed data gathering is not always possible or practical and other methods are used to develop project estimates.","difficulty":"Level: Medium"},{"question":"60.Bottom-up-estimating is another name for overzealous top management estimates.","type":"boolean","answer":"FALSE","help":"Top-down estimates usually are derived from someone who uses experience and/or information to determine the projectduration and total cost. These estimates are sometimes made by top managers who have very little knowledgeof the processes used to complete the project.","difficulty":"Level: Easy"},{"question":"61.The use of past experience is almost always used primarily in the initial phases of a project.","type":"boolean","answer":"TRUE","help":"Past experience is a good starting point for developing time and cost estimates.","difficulty":"Level: Medium"},{"question":"62.Due to the averaging out of under-estimates and over-estimates, a long duration project is more likely to beon target than a short term, small project.Refer to Snapshot from Practice Page 140.","type":"boolean","answer":"FALSE","help":"The smaller the element of a work package, the more accurate the overall estimate is likely to be.","difficulty":"Level: Medium"},{"question":"63.The project structure chosen to manage the project will have little impact on the actual project work to be accomplished.","type":"boolean","answer":"FALSE","help":"Which project structure is chosen to manage the project will influence time and cost estimates.","difficulty":"Level: Medium"},{"question":"64.As long as everyone in a project adds just a little padding to reduce risk, the project duration and costs areprobably overstated by a small amount.","type":"boolean","answer":"FALSE","help":"This phenomenon causes some managers or owners to call for a 10-15 percent cut in time and/or cost for the project.Of course the next time the game is played, the person estimating cost and/or time will pad the estimateto 20 percent or more.","difficulty":"Level: Medium"},{"question":"65.Organization culture can significantly influence project time and cost estimates.","type":"boolean","answer":"TRUE","help":"Organization culture can significantly influence project estimates.","difficulty":"Level: Easy"},{"question":"66.If a project is internal to the company and relatively small, the bottom-up approach to estimating time and costsfor the project is the best choice.Refer to Table 5.1","type":"boolean","answer":"FALSE","help":"See Table 5.1 on page 132.","difficulty":"Level: Easy"},{"question":"67.If time and costs are important to a project the top-down approach to estimating time and costs for the projectis the best choice.","type":"boolean","answer":"FALSE","help":"The bottom-up approach at the work package level can serve as a check on cost elements in the WBS by rollingup the work packages and associated cost accounts to major deliverables. Similarly, resource requirementscan be checked. Later, the time, resource, and cost estimates from the work packages can be consolidatedinto time-phased networks, resource schedules, and budgets that are used for control.","difficulty":"Level: Easy"},{"question":"68.The ideal approach to estimating project time and costs is to use both the top-down and the bottom-up approach.","type":"boolean","answer":"TRUE","help":"The ideal approach is for the project manager to allow enough time for both the top-down and bottom-up estimatesto be worked out so a complete plan based on reliable estimates can be offered to the customer. In this wayfalse expectations are minimized for all stakeholders and negotiation is reduced.","difficulty":"Level: Medium"},{"question":"69.At the strategic level top-down estimating methods are used to evaluate a project proposal.Refer to Table 5.1","type":"boolean","answer":"TRUE","help":"See Table 5.1 on page 132.","difficulty":"Level: Easy"},{"question":"70.Top-down estimates usually are derived from someone who uses experience and/or information to determine the projectduration and total cost.","type":"boolean","answer":"TRUE","help":"Top-down estimates usually are derived from someone who uses experience and/or information to determine the projectduration and total cost.","difficulty":"Level: Easy"},{"question":"71.Estimating the total cost of a house by multiplying the total square feet by a cost per square foot is an exampleof the apportion method of estimating costs.","type":"boolean","answer":"FALSE","help":"Apportionment is used when projects closely follow past projects in features and costs. Given good historicaldata, estimates can be made quickly with little effort and reasonable accuracy. This method is very commonin projects that are relatively standard but have some small variation or customization.","difficulty":"Level: Medium"},{"question":"72.Estimating the total cost of a project by multiplying each major function by a complexity factor is an exampleof the apportion method of estimating costs.","type":"boolean","answer":"FALSE","help":"Apportionment is used when projects closely follow past projects in features and costs. Given good historicaldata, estimates can be made quickly with little effort and reasonable accuracy. This method is very commonin projects that are relatively standard but have some small variation or customization.","difficulty":"Level: Medium"},{"question":"73.Phase estimating is used when a project cannot be rigorously defined because of the uncertainty of design orthe final product.","type":"boolean","answer":"TRUE","help":"Phase estimating is used when an unusual amount of uncertainty surrounds a project and it is impractical to estimatetimes and costs for the entire project.","difficulty":"Level: Medium"},{"question":"74.Phase estimating uses both the bottom-up and top-down methods for estimating project time and costs.","type":"boolean","answer":"TRUE","help":"This approach begins with a top-down estimate for the project and then refines estimates for phases of the projectas it is implemented.","difficulty":"Level: Medium"},{"question":"75.Using a WBS permits the use of different levels of detail for different levels of management.","type":"boolean","answer":"TRUE","help":"Getting the level of detail in the WBS to match management needs for effective implementation is crucial, butthe delicate balance is difficult to find. The level of detail in the WBS varies with the complexity of theproject; the need for control; the project size, cost, duration; and other factors.","difficulty":"Level: Easy"},{"question":"76.The Consensus method of estimating costs is a bottom-up technique.","type":"boolean","answer":"FALSE","help":"These first top-down estimates are only a rough cut and typically occur in the \"conceptual\" stage of the project.","difficulty":"Level: Easy"},{"question":"77.The salary of the project manager and her administrative assistant is classified as direct labor costs.","type":"boolean","answer":"FALSE","help":"Direct project overhead costs can be tied to project deliverables or work packages. Examples include the salaryof the project manager and temporary rental space for the project team.","difficulty":"Level: Medium"},{"question":"78.General and Administrative costs are usually allocated as a percent of the total of a direct cost such as labor,materials, or equipment.","type":"boolean","answer":"TRUE","help":"G&amp;A costs are usually allocated as a percent of total direct cost, or a percent of the total of a specificdirect cost such as labor, materials, or equipment.","difficulty":"Level: Medium"},{"question":"79.The apportion method is a top-down approach that uses the pooled experience of senior and/or middle managersto estimate the total project duration and cost.","type":"boolean","answer":"FALSE","help":"Apportionment is used when projects closely follow past projects in features and costs. Given good historicaldata, estimates can be made quickly with little effort and reasonable accuracy. This method is very commonin projects that are relatively standard but have some small variation or customization.","difficulty":"Level: Easy"},{"question":"80.The function point method of time and cost estimating is best applied to projects that have large, complex physicaldeliverables, such as a bridge or building.","type":"boolean","answer":"FALSE","help":"In the software industry, software development projects are frequently estimated using weighted macro variablescalled \"function points\" or major parameters such as number of inputs, number of outputs, number of inquiries,number of data files, and number of interfaces.Short Answer Questions","difficulty":"Short Answer Questions"},{"question":"81.Identify and briefly describe the two major categories of estimating project time and costs.","type":"shortAnswer","answer":"","help":"1. Top-down estimates made by top management, and 2. bottom-up estimates are made by those responsible for completingthe work packages","difficulty":"Level: Medium"},{"question":"82.Why are the estimates for a project's time and costs important for all phases of a project?","type":"shortAnswer","answer":"","help":"The estimates serve as the standard for comparison of actual and plan throughout the life of a project.","difficulty":"Level: Easy"},{"question":"83.Identify the factors that should be considered to improve the quality of estimates for project times and costs.","type":"shortAnswer","answer":"","help":"1. planning horizon, 2. project duration, 3. people, 4. project structure and organization, 5. padding estimates,6. organization culture, and 7. non-project factors","difficulty":"Level: Difficult"},{"question":"84.Under what conditions would the top-down approach to estimating project times and costs be the best choice?","type":"shortAnswer","answer":"","help":"In the early stages of a project to help develop the initial plan, in making strategic decisions, in projectsof high uncertainty, in small internal projects, or in projects with an unstable scope.","difficulty":"Level: Difficult"},{"question":"85.Under what conditions would the bottom-up approach to estimating project times and costs be the best choice?","type":"shortAnswer","answer":"","help":"When low cost, efficient estimates are needed, when time and cost are important, when working on a fixed pricecontract, or when the customer wants details.","difficulty":"Level: Difficult"},{"question":"86.Describe the ideal approach for a project manager to develop optimal estimates for a project's time and costs.","type":"shortAnswer","answer":"","help":"Allow enough time for both the top-down and bottom-up estimates to be worked out and included in the final plan.","difficulty":"Level: Difficult"},{"question":"87.Identify and briefly describe the five major methods of top-down estimating.","type":"shortAnswer","answer":"","help":"1. consensus, 2. ratio method, 3. apportion method, 4. function point, and 5. learning curves","difficulty":"Level: Difficult"},{"question":"88.Identify and briefly describe the four major methods of bottom-up estimating.","type":"shortAnswer","answer":"","help":"1. template method, 2. parametric procedure applied to specific tasks, 3. detailed estimates from the WBS workpackages, and 4. phase estimating","difficulty":"Level: Difficult"},{"question":"89.Identify the drawbacks to an excessive level of detail in project times and costs.","type":"shortAnswer","answer":"","help":"1. emphasis on departmental outcomes, and 2. increased paperwork","difficulty":"Level: Difficult"},{"question":"90.Identify the three major categories of project costs and give an example of each.","type":"shortAnswer","answer":"","help":"1. Direct costs (labor, materials, equipment, other), 2. Project Overhead Costs (salaries of project manager,rent on space to house the project), and 3. General and Administrative Overhead Costs (advertising, accounting,and senior management of the organization)","difficulty":"Level: Difficult"},{"question":"91.\"The best way to improve estimates is to collect and archive data on past project estimates and actuals.\" Agreeor disagree and support your answer.","type":"shortAnswer","answer":"","help":"This technique is rated as a 'best practice' among leading project management organizations. Several large firmshave large estimating departments that have developed large time and cost databases.5-1","difficulty":"1"}]